So um originally the plan was to talk
more about reinforcement learning but I
thought since I only had one lecture to
give I think this class would be a
little bit incomplete without saying
something about multimodality which is
so pervasive if you look at all the
major models. Um so this will be a
overview of um multimodal models. Um, of
course, this could be a whole class in
itself. Um, and I'll try to do what I
can in one lecture. Okay, so let's dive
into multimodal models. So, so far in
this class, we've have exclusively
focused on language models. And language
models are already pretty general. They
give you the ability to go from any
piece of text to any text. So this could
be any language uh code um you know
poetry any anything you like even you
know let's say uh DNA for example
um but the world is multimodal um you
have text you have images audio video
and if you think about a sort of a north
star of where we want to be is what
people call an omnimodel which is
ability to take any combination of any
of these modalities ities and output any
combination of any of these modalities.
So for example, I can give you an image
and a video and I can ask a question
about you know which uh about the image
and the video. I can generate images. I
can convert the audio into an image. You
can imagine all sorts of different
applications um by having a omni model.
So, you know, in this class, I'm not
going to build up to a whole omni model,
but I'll give you um you know, some of
the pieces that are um at least allow
you to ingest a little bit of um of
images um which we'll mostly focus on
today.
So, so how do you build such a thing?
Well, um this is sort of a a weird way
to motivate this, but um the reality is
that transformers work really well and
despite the best efforts of people to
try other things um those are in across
all these modalities still at scale the
the best thing we have. So we have to
figure out how to use them. And now
transformers were designed for text. So
they have this property that they speak
you know tokens. So they take input as
input a bunch of tokens and then output
some tokens. And here I'm um
sort of expanding the notion of token to
be not just a discrete token that we've
seen in text but also uh potentially
continuous tokens. You can think about
these as embedding of uh tokens.
And the key thing is that a token should
represent some sort of semantic unit of
information. Um for example in natural
language uh tokens are subwords and
these are you know somewhat meaningful
whereas for example a pixel is is
certainly not uh meaningful by itself.
Um so somehow we must convert everything
including you know audio and um and
images into either discrete or
continuous uh tokens.
Now notice that we've already had to do
this even with text right in the first
lecture we talked about tokenization and
there it was um you know not too bad I
mean we had a BP tokenizer you guys
implemented it um it was you know it's
fine um one could wish for um you know a
better tokenizer or no token uh
something that doesn't have tokenizers
at all but um it's not the worst thing
in the world. Um now for non-ext
modalities um we have to scratch our
heads a lot more and figure out what is
the equivalent of the BP tokenizer that
will take an image and produce things
that a transformer can digest.
Okay. So
you have to answer two questions here.
One is for non-ext data for example
images or videos or audio how do you
input these into the transformer and
then how do you generate them out and
this lecture will mostly focus on uh
question number one.
Okay.
So so let's start um back in rewind the
clock back to uh 20 21. Um so the clip
model which some of you might be
familiar with is a lot of the foundation
of uh modern you know uh VLMs and so we
can go through this a bit uh more in
more detail. So, clip stands for
contrastive language image pre-training
and a bit of historical context is
around that time um you know com you
know GPD3 had already happened GP2 all
the language models had already um gone
into this kind of foundation model era
um you know vision was still um you know
there were some efforts but you know
traditionally had been based on large
annotated um data sets such as imageet
and training models um such as the
ResNet on these data sets and doing a
bunch of other things like data
augmentation and getting really good
performance.
And so the researchers at OpenAI were
wondering is it possible to leverage the
large amount of image and textual
captions um out there? So inspired by
this idea in language where you could
just scrape the internet you have all
this text it's very noisy but somehow if
you train a large enough model you can
make sense out of this and generate
something useful. Um so what was the
equivalent of that for for images?
So as a result clip was born and the
idea of clip is uh fairly you know
simple and straightforward. So the idea
here is that suppose I give you a bunch
of image text pairs. So let's say I give
you 32,000 of these. Okay. So what I'm
going to do is for each image I'm going
to encode it using image encoder which
I'll explain later into a vector. Um so
I'm going to have third uh 32,000 of
these um image encodings.
I'm going to also do the same thing with
the corresponding uh text. So that'll
give me uh t1 through tn. Right? So
these are the embeddings of the text.
These are embedding of the images.
Now the objective I want to set up is
that um I want the
you know image let's take I1. So I1 is
associated with aligned with t1 right.
So I want this um alignment
um the dotproduct between these two
embeddings to be much larger than the
dotproduct between I1 and all the other
texts. Okay. And conversely I also want
um for this text to say that this dot
productduct is larger than the
dotproduct between T1 and all the other
images.
So that in a nutshell is the clip
objective and you can imagine doing
there's um basically two to two * n um
different um kind of softmax
classification um you know problems. So
here's um here's the here's the code. So
you get a m byd matrix for the image
encodings and m byd times for the
textual embeddings. You normalize um and
you take the stop product
um with some with some temperature and
then you compute the cross um entropy.
Okay.
So it's basically like a multiclass
classification problem where the
examples are sort of structured in this
kind of um you know n byn matrix form.
Okay. Any questions about that?
All right. So
so this um so some more details about
how clip was built. Um so where does the
data come from? Um there are not you
know too many details in the in the
paper about uh the the data. Roughly
it's um you take a bunch of queries um
uh from somewhere and then you go search
online for these and you mine a bunch of
image and text uh pairs
and um this resulted in 400 million text
image text pairs. um the data set wasn't
released but there was an effort um by
this paper called you know open clip
which uh replicated
and and further kind of extended the
clip ideas um um so there was this data
set called lion 5B which was released
five billion you know images with
textual descriptions and there was a
bunch of processing that happened um
interestingly they actually used clip
for the data filtering and then trained
open clip. Um so you know there's some
bootstrapping happening but at least
this is a model where you can point to
the data set that it was trained on and
um the code as well.
Okay. So, a few other you know details.
Um, so images come in all sorts of
resolutions, right? If you find an
internet image, it might be uh long and
skinny or tall um sorry, long and skinny
or the other way. So, arbitrary
dimensions. And um one thing that you
learn about neuronets is that they don't
like things to be dynamic. they want
things to be you know fixed size. So
there is a sort of somewhat um you know
heristic uh processing that happens is
they resize the image so that the
shorter side is 336 or whatever target
size could be 224 as well. Um and then
they center crop um to get a square.
Okay, this is obviously for convenience.
Later we'll see that you can do much
better than this but this is just for
expediency and also at this time people
were the clip authors were thinking
about image net and classification. So
um usually the object is in the middle
and you're just trimming off some
background so it doesn't matter too
much.
Okay. So um so what is the vision
encoder? So this is the general
algorithm but I've uh haven't specified
what the image and text encoders are.
>> Yeah
and text when they input right. So they
provide text every type of email
generation that we follow will have some
sort of it. That's why they train on
both text and image rather than just
images. So the question I think is why
they train out image text pairs as
opposed to images.
>> Right? So there is a line of work that
tries to encode images um into
representations
um based on data augmentation. So for
example, if you take an image and I
think this idea called sim clear, you
augment it, um you crop it, you randomly
perturb it, um rotate it and you want to
say that that is the same image like
they should have similar embeddings. Um
now the and that's that's useful for
kind of low-level details but um the
problem is that um you won't data
augment your way from like one type of
dog to another dog. So by using that
text it gives you higher level semantic
um um representations of the images
and yeah that's a good question and
later we'll see how these semantic
representations are useful if you look
at the types of tasks that people are
trying to uh solve.
Okay so what is the vision encoder that
clip uses? Um they actually experimented
with a bunch of different ones um
resnats and vision transformers uh which
had just come out and they found out the
vision transformers perform the best. So
when people say clip they usually mean
the vit uh version and so you know a
vision transformer does the following.
Um so you take an image and um you you
break it up into these patches. Um I
think the original paper was like 16 by
16. Um and uh the clip used 14 by 14. Um
but anyway you have these little you
know patches which are basically you
know vectors. So each patch is in some
sense a a well a token for this you know
vision transformer.
um you add the positional embeddings
just like you would if you're training a
a language model and then you just put
it through a standard transformer.
Um and if you want um to you know
classify then you you would um well you
would usually want to um okay so the
trans sorry the transformer encoder
produces a a a sequence of vectors right
and um the clip paper does something a
little bit different you can average all
these vectors that gives you a single
vector u but they saw it was better to
do a attention pooling which means that
you take the global average of all the
activations but then you also do another
round of uh um you know attention with
that query against the key and values of
each position and that gives you another
vector which is maybe a little bit more
um informed rather than just like a a
straightup average.
Okay, so that's uh the vit and um the
clip paper found that the best model is
what is called vit l14.
Um so this to decipher this this is a
large vit um I think it has like 24
layers or so um not quite sure about
that. um and 14x4 patches. Um each patch
is RGB, so it has three channels and um
they trained on 336 by 336 resolution
images. Actually, they trained on lower
res and then they um up you know uh and
then I guess for speed because high
resolution images takes uh longer and
then for the latter part of training
they train on higher res. Yeah.
>> Yeah. for the position embedding would
it be more complicated than text for
example X only has like one dimension
but even has two output down
>> yeah so a question is um can you do be
smarter about the position embeddings
because this is just you know linear
zero through nine um I think in this
paper they actually in the clip paper I
believe they tried some 2D version of
this and the 1DNA they found that it
doesn't really that matter that much.
Um, I think it's also,
you know, I always have to take these
results with a with the idea that
they're interesting classification in
mind. So, for classification, maybe it
doesn't matter. Later, we'll see fancier
positional embeddings that do take into
account the um the spatial structure.
Okay. So the text encoder um is a
standard transformer. It's a GPT2 style
transformer since um that was from the
same group that developed GPT2.
And um in order to get a single vector
out of a sequence um they prepended BOS
and um appended EOS and then they took
EOS um the activation at the highest
layer as the um the representation of
that whole sequence.
Okay. Okay, so you have the vision
encoder, you have the text encoder, and
then you can do this um process to to
train. Uh you pick a batch, you encode
all the text, you code all the images,
and then you form these um two end cross
entropy losses and then you go from
there.
Okay, so the headline result and which
got a lot of people excited about clip
back in 2021 is that on the imageet
benchmark, zero shot clip outperformed a
resnet that was trained on 1.2 million
imageet images. So if you think about
this 1.2 to image net images. This was
many many hours of Amazon Mechanical
Turk worker time to do this annotation.
Um, and now you have clip that was
trained on more organic you know web
data. Um, of course this was the labor
of a bunch of people on the web but you
know if you're able to leverage that or
existing data already then you can just
zero it. And the zeroot technique is
basically um to to explain I don't have
slide support here but you take an image
and then you have a bunch of text and
then you basically take the dot product
with the various labels and see which
one's the highest.
Oh yeah it is. Sorry it is on this part
of the site. Okay good point. So this is
a zero shop uh prediction um where you
take an image and then you Yeah, what I
said.
>> Cool. Any questions?
>> Yeah. this type of sound supervised
version is actually an issue if uh for
example there's a dog image like for all
the caption but maybe not just this
simple
this dog maybe other caption also would
that confuse the model
>> yeah so the question is if you have a
dog and there's maybe other captions
that also have dogs would that confuse
the model um in general this process is
going to be noisy um I it's okay if
there's another dog because on average
um it's unlikely that there's always
going to be a dog. Sometimes it's going
to be apple or a cat or something.
Um but but also another point is that
these images are um basically scraped
from images on the web with textual text
next to them or in the alt um kind of a
image. And so they're extremely noisy.
There's been, you know, studies that
look at when you have a caption of a of
a image, it doesn't necessarily just
like verbatim say what's in the image,
right? Because if you have an image and
it's a dog, you don't need to say a dog.
It's um so this is process is very
noisy. So it's um maybe
uh kind of somewhat surprising but also
interesting that it worked. I mean there
was a lot of data filtering that is
needed. So if you take arbitrary images
on text on that web, it's probably going
to be too way too noisy.
One other thing to note which um relates
to a point I'll come back to at the very
end is they also try this um alternative
where instead of doing this ranking,
they can predict text from the images.
So they can set an objective where they
try to take the images and predict the
text um either as a bag of words or um
as a language model and they show that
you know maybe I don't know somewhat
surprisingly that if you use a stronger
model it actually does does worse or at
least is less efficient um compared to
using bag of words um you know clip.
So this is saying that this is you know
I I think saying that for the actually
the representations that uh you're
trying to learn or again this is image
net accuracy so it's classification um
actually modeling the exact token
sequences of of the caption isn't um so
important for getting the rough um
representation of the image.
Okay, we'll come back to this uh point
at the at the end. Um, so so what do we
learned so far? Um, so we've encoded
images using clip and it captures the
semantics of the image because it's
paired with text and generally text
talks about the the semantics. Um, it is
important to note that the design
decisions here are based on image
classification. So it's not very, you
know, fine grained. Um, but yet it
still, as we'll say, serves a as a kind
of robust starting point for everything
we're going to do later.
One technical kind of downside of clip
is that it does require large uh, you
know, batch sizes like 30,000. Um, if if
you have a batch size of one, clearly it
doesn't work or even 10, it doesn't
work. And furthermore, the softmax
operation operates over the full batch.
So it's not really very decomposible.
Whereas if you think about normal
language model training um a batch of
examples all the sequences kind of
paralyze and you just like do a um a
aggregation at the at the end.
So this point will be addressed by
another uh paper um from Google that uh
came out called cichlip. And so think
about this as basically an improved
version of clip. So it stands for
sigmoid loss for language image
pre-training. Um and here the the main
difference is that clip does multiclass
classification. It says I have this
aligned text and image and I'm going to
say this is positive and against all the
other alternative images or against all
the alternative texts. cichlip in some
sense is a lot simpler. It basically
says for any given image text pair
are they aligned or not? Right? So if I
reference this diagram up here, it's
basically binary classification where
the diagonals are positive examples and
the off diagonal are negative examples.
That's it.
So so here's the algorithm. um you take
the embeddings, you normalize, you take
the dotproduct as usual uh but now
you're uh doing um you're forming the
labels which are minus one on off
diagonal and diagonals you have one um
and then you do a um you know log
sigmoid.
So the objective is very simple. Yeah.
little first as the sampling structure
because I think most of the samples are
not quite
so random cycling
the laws I think will
>> yeah so the question is does this
require any sophisticated sampling uh
strategies um at least in the initial
paper they were just operating on
literally the same type of matrix um you
could imagine I You're probably thinking
in general for kind of these contrastive
methods like the negative examples need
to be sometimes you need to balance the
positives and the negatives or the
negatives need to be like tight
negatives so that you're not biased but
um at least in the initial version this
was you know fairly just
straightforward.
So um to speak about the data um you
know uh this was done at Google this was
a data set they used another paper which
was another image language image model
around 2022 which got a web li data set
with you know order billion image text
pairs um they also do did some extra
work for example image that had text in
them they did OCR and that's another way
to form text image pairs and did some
filtering ing this was multilingual. Um
the main um po you know uh point of this
this paper was that it was much more
efficient to train than than clip. Um so
clip was trained uh 10 days on 256 uh
TPU v3s and cichlip was 5 days on 32 v4s
and you might think oh v4s are actually
should be faster than v3s in terms of
flops per second they're actually not.
um they're better because you can put
more of them in a pod and the
interconnect is better. But um at this
scale it's really um actually you know
not um not faster actually you know uh
like 60% slower or something. Um so the
the the way that this is uh you know
faster and of course I think clip
probably did not try to optimize the the
code for the maximum you know
throughput. it was just kind of let's
get this thing to work. Um but the cig
paper showed that you can um you know
parallelize this as follows. So you have
basically and if you recall your kind of
systems um lecture. So this is can think
about it as you know DDP if if you if
you like where each device is um uh
stores a subset of the the you know
image text pairs. Um however there's
interactions between the examples unlike
in language model training where
everything just factors. So in the first
uh pass um each device just computes all
the losses on um on the its whatever
image uh text pairs it has locally
um and and then and then you you send um
the text. So basically device one gets
uh T5 through T8 and now it's able to
compute the negatives here and then it
gets uh T9 through T12. So you kind of
rotate around until you cover all the
the off diagonal uh block entries.
Um another thing that uh they
was nice about cichlip is that you
effectively decoupling batch size from
the loss. Um whereas in clip the loss is
tied to the batch size. If you change
the batch size it's a different loss
function. Um so they were able to
experiment with much smaller batch sizes
um less than you know 16k and in that
regime um it's much better than clip
because the loss function if you have
too many too uh small of a batch size is
just degrades whereas um for smaller
batch size for cichlip um you have more
variance but um but it's the same in
expectation is the same loss. Um they
also say wow you can go up to large much
larger batch sizes but that doesn't
really help. Um and we saw that critical
batch sizes uh at some limit and 32k was
their essentially their critical batch
size.
Okay. So now we have clip and cig. Um
these are image encoders that take an
image um in this version just a fixed
size image 336 x 336 let's say and maps
it into a vector okay which uh contains
um some you know semantics.
So now let's start building um um VLMs,
vision language models. And I'm going to
talk about two families of models um
Lava and Quen. Um the two are very
similar in the sort of broad template.
There are some details that are
different which we'll we'll go through.
And the basic idea is that we're going
to take these embeddings and then just
inject them into a language model. So
this is going to be more of a flavor of
sort of mid-training or post-training
where uh we take an existing image
encoder, we take an existing LLM and
then we're going to kind of stitch it
together rather than training something
from scratch.
Okay. So the LA lava paper came out in
2023.
Um and this got people excited because
um at around this time all the you know
the closed models um like GPD I think it
was GPD4 was able to do kind of visual
reasoning and um they were able to show
that they could do some visual reasoning
as well. It wasn't as good as GPD4 of
course uh but um but you know I think it
was an open model and people got to see
what went under the hood.
So um for VLMs there's essentially uh a
few pieces here. Um there's a vision
encoder. They use clip here. For the
text decoder they use a language model
called Vunia which is the the first
llama model that was fine-tuned on some
shared GPT conversations. So these are
uh conversations that people had with
chat GPT and shared them on this
website. I don't think this is up
anymore.
Um so the data that they used was um
based on
um MS uh Coco. So this was an annotated
data set where they had mechanical Turk
workers go and annotate a bunch of
images with bounding boxes and captions
describing what was in the image. Um so
they basically synthesized a a data set
for their model. So they prompted GPT4
with the captions or the detected
objects and asked GPT4 to generate
questions or conversations. Um for
example um this is an image in the MSCO
data set. This was an annotated um
caption done by a human and also uh here
is the you know also annotated by a
human. Um and then you ask GPD4 generate
uh me a conversation and you might get a
a question and an answer. Uh you might
ask GPD4 generate me a detailed
description. It generates something I
guess similar to the caption and then
you can ask GP4 to generate complex
reasoning and it does um you know
something like that.
Okay. So this is syn syn synthesized uh
data 158,000
examples
um and and then they you know trained a
model on this. So the model um so they
use they use clip um in particular the
the highest performing clip uh version
VITL14
um so 14x4 patches
um and then they let's just look at this
image um so they take images they send
it through this vision encoder clip that
gives you a vector but this vector isn't
really in the same space so to speak as
the text. So then they um multiply by
matrix W to get another vector which is
in the same space as the texture
embeddings. And for text you basically
just use your standard embeddings to get
vectors.
So what's basically happening is that
the text gets encoded into these vectors
and the image also gets encoded into
these these vectors and then these
vectors this whole sequence of vectors
just goes through a standard transformer
and produces output.
Okay, so we're in some sense converting
these images into textual tokens um so I
can leverage the pre-trained uh language
model.
Um so to train this model um they do uh
it two in two stages. The first stage is
that they they freeze the vision encoder
and the language model and only train
this matrix W. And this is what they
call the alignment phase which is
essentially making sure that the the
image um gets mapped into kind of the
same you know space because if you just
use a random W um these these images are
not going to be um I mean certainly
they're not embeddings representing any
sort of like natural language token. So
the goal of training W is that they sort
of look like natural language token
embeddings.
And the second stage is that they now
still freeze the vision encoder and then
train W and the language model. So
they're fine-tuning the language model
on on um their their data. So remember
their data is basically here's an image
and here is a conversation or
description or complex uh you know
reasoning example.
So this is all image plus text to text.
Okay. So um this is one example from
their paper. Uh it's kind of
interesting. So you have an input image
and um a conversation. The user says
what's unusual about this image? And
their model is able to tell you that uh
you don't usually iron on the back of a
minivan. Um, and they also make a point
that their model is is pretty good
because even if your your user um uh
prompt is not really prompting like the
unusualness, it still talks about it
whereas um you know GP4 obviously is
able to do this but uh other models at
the time uh were not um able to.
Okay, any questions about lava?
Okay, so that was 2023. Um, and I'm
going to sort of skip forward to uh Lava
1 vision, which is 2024. There was a
sequence of papers after the Lava paper
came out of Lava 1.5, Lava Next. Um, and
the main but but I'll capture all of
these innovations I think in what I'll
describe next. Um the main thing that
they did is it's essentially the same
recipe but they were trying to be more
ambitious in terms of the types of
multimodal applications they could do.
So they um were able to handle multiple
images and videos. So here's the same uh
sort of diagram. Now they can take an
image, a single image or multiple images
or a video which is essentially a
sequence of images um corresponding to a
sampling of the frames. Um
and here the vision encoder they
upgraded to cichlip. Um the text decoder
they use Quen 2 now which was um
probably the best uh language model um
that was out at that time. And then for
the uh projector or the adapter which is
the thing that takes the output of the
vision encoder and turns it into the
input of the the language model is a
two-layer MLP instead of a linear
projection.
Okay. So relatively you know it's like
you have a system and you're just like
upgrading the parts but it's the same
kind of rough system. Um so the let's
talk a little bit about data processing.
Um
so one thing that they wanted to do is
to do OCR
and the thing with OCR is that you need
to preserve very fine grain information.
Um otherwise a J looks like a I and
that's that's not good. Um so remember
that clip resizes and crops to 336 by
336. And clearly if you have a document
and you crop to 336 x36 you can't read
it. So uh their solution is this idea
called any res uh which was actually
introduced in the lava 1.5 paper and the
idea is basically um I mean it's fairly
straightforward. you break up an image
into, you know, multiple, you know,
pieces. Um, and the idea is that each
piece is the resolution of whatever the
vision encoder is going to take, 336 x
336, for example. So, you're going to
code all the pieces and then you can
into a bunch of vectors and then you
concatenate the vectors. Okay? So,
you're you're basically noticing that
your vision encoder can't handle high
resolution. So rather than downsampling,
you're just going to uh crop and look at
different parts of the image.
And now if you have really super high
resolution images or videos, then you
get too many tokens. So then they have
to then they sort of down uh sample. But
um the idea behind any res is that it's
sort of adaptive. And this is sort of
nice because the transformer is already
adaptive. Language can be your sentences
can be any length. And the transformer
already handles that pretty well. So it
turns out images can be any resolution.
So that's kind of picking back on the
same um kind of dynamic uh ability.
Um so here is uh what they actually do
for for images here. So let's say you
have this image of a of a paper. Um they
do down sample and have one path which
is basically a down sampled encoding of
the entire paper. But then they break it
up into these chunks where each chunk is
the resolution that the vision encoder
expects and then encodes each of these
separately. And then you concatenate all
these patches and if you have too many
then you sort of you know reduce that
the number of patches and by um
interpolation.
So okay so then they're able to handle
images multiple images and video. So you
think about well you know all of these
are technically all reducible to images
but they put their thumb on a scale a
little bit because um they want to make
sure all the modalities are kind of
roughly uh you know comparable um
because videos can be very long. They
don't want their data set to be
dominated by a bunch of like repetitive
you know frames. So here's what they do
here. So for a single image they
basically have the full image
downsampled and then a bunch of crops um
up to n crops there up to nine. And if
you are presented with multiple images
then they just uh use the sort of the
you know the base base resolution. So if
you have a single image I get to look at
it more carefully. If I have multiple
images I'm just going to look at it kind
of from um you know afar. And for video
um we're going to use um even kind of
lower resolution or fewer tokens to
represent each frame because the idea is
that well videos can be um you know they
only use up to 32 frames. Um
uh but you know the the you start
running into kind of context length uh
problems uh for video
and later we'll see how you know a big
part of being able to handle multimodal
is is to deal with long context.
Okay. So um the data
here that they use is um is I would say
that they state the philosophy is like
they want to curate high quality data
and quantity. Another way to interpret
this is that it's very targeted uh data.
If you look at many of these it's like
very taskbased whether you're doing
visual question answering or um you know
answering questions about tables. So it
this is definitely kind of post-training
you know territory where you're you're
trying to get your model to do these
tasks and therefore you create a bunch
of these tasks and this this work is
also um unabashedly
basically you know distilling GPT4 um
you know models so that they can get the
best you know performance which is um I
guess not ideal but um this is what uh
you do if you don't have a annotation
budget. Um
and uh so they have single images,
multiple images and videos. So there's a
lot of different um you know uh you know
pieces. Some of these are very specific
like you give two images and you're
trying to spot the difference. Um but
one thing that uh okay I'll talk about
I'll come back to this at this point
later. So for training it's um roughly
the same idea as before where the first
stage is that you're focused on uh
alignment.
So um you know in particular you only
train you know the projector which is
the adapter.
Um and then in the second stage you
train and the third stage is you train
the full model. And before we had two
stages, now we have three stages. Um I
think you know I'm not sure there's any
particular principle reason for this
except for the second stage is trying to
put high quality data but more focusing
on knowledge and um the final stage is
uh focusing on examples that look like
your downstream tasks.
Okay. So one thing that they um found in
this paper which was kind of interesting
is um that you get transfer between
modalities.
So even though they have only single
image data for diagrams and charts but
this actually generalizes to the
multiple images. So at test time it's ne
at training time it never saw um example
where you have a table and a chart and
you're asking questions about it. But at
test time, you have a t um you have two
images, one for uh the the table and one
for the chart, and you're able to have
some sort of conversation about it. um
at training time you only have OCR data
on single image data and you only have
relational reasoning for multiple images
but you can generalize to these uh cases
where um which are useful for powering
guey agents where you show it a bunch of
you know screenshots this is multiple
images and it can generate um a
description of the the the screenshots.
Um another example is that um they have
this idea of visual prompting u where uh
you have this circle which is a part of
the image but that's meant to highlight
the part of the image that you're
supposed to you know do something about.
Um and this type of data only exists for
single images and now it can generalize
to um you know videos where the user
says describe the player highlighted in
the video and this player is across
multiple frames.
So this is you know when I first look at
this um and I said oh boy you know
you're basically targeting each of these
tasks. is kind of like supervised
learning. But um but if you have enough
tasks, these models seem to do do some
transfer um which is which is uh I guess
reassuring.
Okay, so again this is a fairly standard
uh VLM template vision encoder plus the
projector um into the language model. Um
there's a lot of work that goes into the
the data curation. and they lean pretty
heavily into synthesize task specific
data. Um the nice thing about the Lava
series is that it it's one of the few
works that open sources. They're not
just the model weights but also the
data. So you can really replicate and
study this stuff.
Okay. Now let's talk about uh Quen
models. Um so Quend started also
training in 2023 multimodal models. So
the first version was QuenVL
and uh hopefully I'll go through this
quickly because you hopefully see the
pattern. The vision encoder they used
open clip um remember open clip was a
open reproductions of of a clip model.
Um so it's basically a clip um encoder.
Um and they for the adapter
um they did one layer of cross attention
incorporate 2D positional embeddings and
maps to a fixed size of you know uh 256
which is a little bit you know I I guess
uh
I guess this will be changed later um
because this is definitely not very
dynamic but neither is the vision
encoder at this point. Um I guess this
got caught off but uh um but uh the
special tokens are like they have an
image tag and a box tag for bounding box
and a ref tag for um description.
This is what happens when your slides
are in HTML. Um so for training they
have three stages just like with the
lava models. In the first stage, um the
idea is to I mean they call it
pre-training but it's really you know
you're not pre-training from scratch. Um
they uh this is generally large scale
lowquality data. They freeze the um the
language model and train the vision
encoder and adapter. Um so this is a bit
different in that from um the lava
models in that they train the vision
encoder um and at this point um and you
can see some of the data sets that they
um are are training on 1.4 for you know
billion examples. Stage two they move to
higher quality task specific data and
you can see some of the kind of the
usual suspects of like VQA data sets um
you know chart question answering and so
on. Um and then they train all the
parameters here. And finally stage three
is um you uh instruction tuning data. Um
you freeze the visual encoder and you
train um the the adapter in the language
model. Um here are some examples of the
type of things that they're able to do.
So um of course this is Quen. So may
some of these examples are in in in
Chinese. um their interest is also
making a model that is supposed to be
sometimes subsuming a language model. So
a language model can do code. So we want
the vision model to be good at code as
well. Um and the you can have this
example if you can see it is an image
and can fight Spider-Man the Hulk and it
can output bounding boxes um you know as
well. It doesn't actually output an
image. It just outputs um uh you know a
bounding box.
Um and then you can do OCR. You can
compare um you know. So use your stuff.
Um okay. So then Quinn 2 um was um again
a kind of upgrade. There's some new
ideas here which I'll go through. Um so
they use a larger vision encoder. Um
they also started doing uh dynamic
resolution. I think this was the main
thing we remember when we went from lava
to lava one vision they realized oh we
need to handle images and of different
sizes and if you try to do video you
it's clear that you need some sort of
dynamic resolution. So um the model is
is basically so let's say you have this
this uh picture here that uh might be
mapped to um 11,000 tokens. This tiny
picture of a equation might be only
mapped to eight tokens um and so on and
so forth. Um so how do they um you know
do this? Well, basically each um it's a
kind of the same idea of the NRA idea
from lava where each uh 224x 224 patch
is encoded with a vit um and remember
the vit that they started with is the
open clip vit but this gets um you know
uh fine-tuned
um and then they try trying to reduce
the context size they uh compress every
2x two into one. So that they ultimately
every patch uh gets um generates 66
tokens for videos. They sample two
frames a second but you know max out at
16,000 you know tokens. Um
um okay so one thing coming back to this
question about positional embeddings um
so they did do something different uh
here with Quen 2. Um so they use this
idea called multimodal rotary uh
multimodal rope. So remember we saw rope
before and the idea behind rope is that
you have a um you know embedding such
that the
um you know the inner product between
the vectors kind of depends only on the
kind of distance. So the distance is
defined in 1D by just the number of
tokens you're away from it. So now uh
the multi-dimensional version is
essentially the same thing except for
now you have um 3D. So you have height,
you have width and you have time. So
each position, each patch now is a a
triple uh defined by the the
coordinates. And then to compute the M
rope, you basically for every dimension
you compute the rope and then you
concatenate. Okay, so it's a fairly, you
know, straightforward um idea. Although
later with Quen 3, we'll see how this is
actually um a bit sub-optimal.
Um okay, so they initialize the language
model with, you know, this is the Quenv
model. So of course they're initializing
with Quen. Um and then they have three
stages of training um which is very
similar to um what bef we did before.
And then they were able to show a bunch
of you know different capabilities
um you know some video understanding um
you know it can do math and code
function calling um and and so on so
forth.
Okay. So quickly I'll talk about Quen 3.
Um so again there's a few kind of
changes here. Um I wouldn't say these
are kind of structural big changes but
they are probably changes that do impact
the the quality of the model. So this is
from last year Quen 3VL report. Um and
so it's a roughly the same uh diagram
here. I'll point out a you know maybe a
I'll come back to this diagram. I'll um
go through some of the changes. So one
is that now they're using quen 3 models.
They have a a series of dense ande
models and the quen 3 models are you
know really really good and it really
helps the quality of the final model. Um
one thing that they are invested in is
long context understanding. So their
context length can go up to 256K
which is uh really important if you're
trying to do long video. Um let's talk
about the vision encoder. So they use
cichlip 2 which is basically improved
version of cichlip. It's actually an
identical architecture is designed to be
backward compatible. Um and then um they
improved their rope and um the way to
explain this is before you had the three
dimensions time, width and height and uh
basically uh going to
ba um basically allocate the first block
of uh dimensions to the time then the
next block to width and the next to
height. And the problem if you remember
um rope is that you know each uh
component refers represents a different
you know frequency. So this would mean
that maybe all the temporal dimensions
are low frequency and all the height
dimensions are high frequency. So they
basically interle them um when they
realize that and they now um all the the
axes are exposed to both low and high
frequency.
Um another thing they did was explicit
video uh timestamps. Um so if you look
at closely at this uh sorry this was
wait okay this is quant three. Oops. Um
so if you look uh this is probably a
little bit too small but um before the
time stamp was kind of implicit in the
the positional encodings right each
frame in a video intrinsically gets a
different you know uh there's a notion
of time just because it's in a different
position. Um but here they made the time
explicit. So these are actually token 0
seconds is a token that is is now you
have a token that represents the time.
Um and they found this uh you know to be
helpful presumably because it's
something that you can directly refer to
like what happened at you know after two
seconds.
Um so that is the main uh one of the
main changes.
um they also did this square root
normalized per token loss. So the idea
is that you know some examples that call
video are very long and some examples
that involve a single image are very
short and the normal thing is that every
token is treated the same and this would
mean that the video examples are going
to you know you know dominate. Uh so
they basically um the details aren't too
clear but I I believe they um normalized
each example by the uh square root of
the um the length uh to basically
downweight the impact of really long
examples.
Um the the final thing that is uh worth
noting which is interesting is that they
did something interesting with adapter.
So remember we start the adapter is a
thing that connects the vision encoder
to the language model and lava was the
simplest. It was just a linear
projection and then we got an MLP and we
got some cross attention and uh deep
stack which is actually a paper from the
deepseek uh team u but when you know
used here is uh is more sophisticated.
um they noticed that well the vision
coder already computes a stack of um you
know vision uh you know embeddings and
we're basically going to basically add
these directly into the residual stream
of of the um the language model. Okay.
So this is sort of a bit more of a kind
of a deep fusion of the the vision um
encoder into the language model um as
opposed to the vision encoder is a black
box that just outputs a sequence of
vectors.
Okay. So training um is uh so they have
two phases. Um pre-training has actually
four stages, post- training has three
stages. So this you know you can see
that this pipelines are getting quite uh
complicated now. Um so they first train
the adapter this is the same as all
these models and then they have three
stages where they progressively train on
longer and longer sequences from 8k to
32k to 2 56 uh k. Uh most of the tokens
are in the stages two and three. Um and
and then for post- training they do SFT
on long uh chain of thought data,
knowledge distillation and then some
reinforcement learning. Um um at this
point it's really kind of a systems
paper. There's you know there's a bunch
of I highlighted the kind of the core
new ideas but there's a lot of details
that are are are different. And if you
look at the final results the this is a
pretty uh pretty good model. I mean if
you look at these benchmarks as compared
to the closed models Gemini um GPD5 and
Opus 4.1 um you know these these numbers
are um the bold means that it's the the
best number in that in that row. So the
quen models are actually quite quite
strong.
Okay maybe the yeah question
So, we're going to have
Yeah.
>> Yeah.
>> So the question is how do you if what
about video generation and how do you
know whether there it should be a video
or text. So first of all these models
don't generate video videos or images.
The video all the multimodal stuff is on
input side. you're always generating uh
text
and so
um and then you're always in most of
these stages except for RL you're
supervising every token. So there's no
you know uh LM as a judge or quality on
how um well um the the description is
working. It's just basically whatever is
in your data set. Now with RL you can
play around with different you know
reports.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. Um I want to ask is the training
of multiple model
than training the pure LM from those
system perspective perspective.
for system. I think um the most um band
would be used in uh images videos
that test and from side I think uh image
videos they have more to
so that
be
>> yeah so the two questions are um are
training multimodal models harder on the
system side and I mean certainly it's
not easier um um I think you pointed out
that um the data sets are larger video
data is just like you know even loading
it can be bquares um generally we have
not really focused on data loading for
talking about language models because
it's very very cheap so that needs to be
um taken into account and you know all
the same principles of making sure that
your data loading is happening async
with actual computation needs to be
taken into account. And the second uh
part was um sorry what was this second
question?
>> They have more tokens.
>> Oh yeah. So the videos and images can
have more especially video have more
tokens. So um that's one reason we saw
this kind of normalization to to make
sure that we're not um you know giving
more weight to video. I mean you can
always downweight. So if you have more
tokens, if you don't like that, you can
uh downweight. Um we talked to in the
last or uh two weeks ago about like data
mixtures. So you can always kind of
weight things according to whatever um
you know makes sense. Um but there's
also a lot of text tokens out there. So
I think in general um if you look at
yeah the models are trained on like tens
of trillions of tokens. Um, I think
there's a Yeah, I wouldn't say that the
number of multimodal tokens like vastly
outnumbers text tokens.
>> Yeah. Oh, I think you were first.
>> Yeah.
Yeah. So the question is um when you do
this alignment um how does it know what
the language is the model language model
uh pre-trained and it's definitely has
to be pre-trained because otherwise
there's it doesn't make sense to align
it. So the language model is frozen and
you're just training the adapter to
connect the the given uh vision encoder
with the with a given uh language model.
And uh the way you train it is well you
pick a token budget 67 billion um you
know tokens and you just train. There's
not a like adaptive threshold here.
>> Yeah. also let me know about the
difference between the brand number.
So I notically
this the size of the vision
that
So
>> yeah. So the question is are um the
number of parameters in the vision code
are much uh smaller and the answer is uh
yes in general. I'm trying to find um
where is the other place I
um
not here. Okay. Um
the reason is that the vision encoder is
in some sense doing a very local you
know operation. It's looking at a patch.
A patch is very small and it's just
trying to understand the patches.
There's not much knowledge. Um so to
patch we're not reasoning. So most of
the capabilities of the model are are
still kind of in the language model. Um
I'm trying to find the
okay where maybe it was up here. Okay. I
can't Oh yeah. Um so if you look at the
lava model so the full so it's 72
billion parameter language model um and
um
show you what
okay I don't know why this number is uh
so oh this sorry this is 72 million okay
so this is uh much smaller the projector
is much smaller and the the vit is
generally less than a billion you know
uh parameters. Um yeah I guess mostly
because it's fairly um kind of a local
operation. I guess that's the easy way
to say it. Okay, I'm going to think some
other questions. I'm going to try to
move on now. Um so
so I guess quen 3 is a kind of the the
last vision language model I'll talk
about. this got uh save our performance.
Um
um there's a lot of you know data work
that happens not too many details about
the data and the data mix um in these
later quen models. Um so you'll have to
look at um the lava paper or the um the
AI2 has a mobile paper which I didn't
get a chance to talk about that has more
details here. Um and you know from Quen
to Quen to Quen 3 many of these changes
were mostly
um you know there's some kind of changes
there um but the overall framework is
remains the same and mostly it's kind of
scaling up curating more data sets
noticing that you know your long context
isn't you have to handle long context
and maybe sharpening your image
processing and so on.
Okay. So, I'm going to now jump to um
something quite different.
So, there's this paper called Chameleon
from Meta in 2024.
Um so, so far VLMs encode images into
these vectors and then they inject them
into a language model. And because it's
a language model, you can only generate
text. you can't generate you know
images. Um
so
you know there's many ways you can go
about fixing this. You can just take a
VLM. You can also attach a diffusion
head and you now you can generate images
or but I want to talk about this you
know idea here which is chameleon says
what if we mapped everything into
discrete you know tokens
and in some ways aesthetically this is
uh well maybe this reflects that I'm a
language person this is kind of
appealing um um because now you can
analyze and generate images in the same
way everything is a discrete token If
you want to do um you know uh you know
what let's say you want to generate you
know images uh you can say here is a
here's a text prompt and then you can
you know just you know these are more
just tokens that you can generate or you
can kind of uh flip flip uh the you know
the language and the text around as
well. um they have these examples um and
from the command paper you can prompt um
and saying I'm bored can you show me
some birds and then it would be text and
then there' be images and then some more
text and some images so it's interled
and you don't so the in some sense the
vision of an omni model is that text and
images truly live in the same space and
this is accomplished by um making
everything look like text that's one way
to do it okay so I'll talk a a little
bit about how this is done. So the thing
um to you need to do now um is to map
images into discrete tokens. So there's
this idea rather old uh from um
uh from or 2017
which is called vector quantized
variation encoder and the basic idea
here is to uh map an image into um a
discrete code and what you learn is a
mapping that maps this into a continuous
uh vector and this gets sort of rounded
to the nearest code. So you have a code
book which has let's say 8,000 uh codes.
So these are like prototypical
uh vectors that correspond to what you
know patches and then so you pick uh you
know one of these that's the closest and
that would be your representation. So
that's your encoder. It goes through a
continuous phase and then you sort of
round it to the nearest code. And now
the decoder is you take that code and
you try to reconstruct the image and
then you train these VQEs by um you know
uh basically minimizing the
reconstruction loss. Um there's some
other terms that you add because this is
not differentiable um which I won't have
time to get into.
Okay, but at the end of the day, you
have 512 x 512 images that are converted
into a,024 tokens. Um, and each token is
kind comes from a vocabulary of 8,000.
Okay. So now you have basically text,
you have your images, um, which are
basically these codes. um they train a
new tokenizer uh to you know now because
now you have different sort of your data
looks different than if it were just um
normal uh natural language. Um the
training is is um now actually very
straightforward. This is just normal
language model training, right? There's
no adapter, there's no um you know turn
the vision encoder or there's there's
just a language model now. So this is
the part that's kind of appealing. Um so
there's still two stages but you know
even for language model training there's
usually two or more stages where the
first stage is the bulk of training is
large unsupervised
um they have you know both text and text
and image um and then stage two they mix
in high quality data.
Okay, so this is really great and and
elegant. Um there's a few problems with
this. One is that um they found that the
training was not stable. And the reason
is that you know text and images despite
occupying the same space just behave
very differently.
So just calling things discrete tokens
isn't really, you know, isn't hiding the
fact that there's an image living there.
And in particular, text tokens, if you
think about predicting the next word,
this has relatively lower entropy. Most
words are kind of predictable, whereas
image tokens um have very high entropy.
I don't know what shade of blue this
exact token is going to be. Um and so as
a result they found that this training
with this kind of mixture led to a lot
of the norms of um the parameters to
grow um and to generate kind of loss um
instability. They were able to kind of
mitigate or fix this to some extent via
via QK norm and Z loss regularization
which controls the norm growth. Um so so
um I'm not even going to uh show the
results but um I wanted to highlight
this work because there's a certain
elegance here because it's just one
model that treats really all modalities
the same. But the downside is that um it
turned out this model was not really as
performant and the discretization does
definitely loses information. Um so
think about uh you know OCR um you know
again if you discretise
um you know very small print you're not
going to be able to read it anymore. And
finally training with multimodalities is
also tricky. We kind of saw this a
little bit with the quen models and we
had to you know play around with the
weights but this is more exacerbated
here. So you know VKU VAEs were kind of
popular for a while and then and in fact
you know many people were using this for
image generation. The main reason to do
that is well you have a transformer um
how do you generate from a transformer?
You well you have to generate discrete
things and you basically put all your
you know data into this discrete form.
But then you know diffusion models uh
came out um and became popular and
viable for generation. So this flavor of
method is sort of uh less uh less
popular than it used to be.
Okay. So um maybe just kind of reflect
and summarize here. Um you know frontier
models these days are expected to be
multimodal or even more strongly
natively multimodal or omnimodels. Um,
you know, unfortunately there's, you
know, I think when Gemini comes out or
GPD comes out, they tout are touted as
being natively multimodal and handle all
these modalities and in fact they do.
Um, but of course there's no details
about how these are are built. Um I
think that you know it's probably some
you know combination of uh having a
continuous encoder because you don't
want to lose information and then
diffusion for the generation because but
that's you know my speculation. Um you
know the fundamental challenge I think
when you're dealing with multimodality
is how do you handle non-ext modalities?
Um it's also interesting that there's a
symmetry between you know understanding
the modality and generation and there's
different there's no one universal
encoder let's say for example in when we
looked at clip um you only cared for
classification to capture high level
semantics so these vectors could be
fairly small and capture the high level
semantics whereas if you wanted to do
OCR or whether you wanted to generate an
image then you need really fine grain
detail like you need to um that's why
diffusion is so good because it can like
really micro um optimize the the the low
high frequency information
um you know I think in general when
you're dealing with multimodalities
uh you have to think carefully about um
weighing them properly
um for example video certainly has lower
information density than text um so you
don't want a video to overwhelm your
your your text. Um and like I said
before um perhaps the at least the
current best um thing is having
continuous encoders. You know even you
know it seems like even clip even though
it's five years old or similar ideas are
still kind of the go-to way to capture
semantics of of of images. Transformers
are still there. Um and then uh
diffusion models which I didn't talk
about are are great for you know
generation.
Okay so I will stop there. Um that's uh
it for
um the lecture on multi modality. Um I
guess we don't have any homework on uh
doing this but if you're curious um it
would be I think I encourage you to play
around with um you know training some of
these models.